hello and welcome back to introduction
to machine learning I'm ludik bman and
in this video I will tell you about
random forests in a nutshell in the end
you should understand the basic concept
of random Forest you should know some
basic aggregation rules and understand
at least a basic concept of feature
importance what is a random Forest you
already know tree learners and with
random forests we try to stabilize those
tree Learners by begging begging is
short for boot strap
agregation and I will explain you what
bootstrap aggregation
means so what happens here is we have
again labeled training data set with
three
observations three features and one
categorical Target Vari
variable so what bootstrap means is that
we generate new training data sets out
of the one training data set that we
have yeah so we can't we cannot
magically come up with new observations
so what we do is we just draw with
replacement from the training data so if
you look at the first bootstrap sample
that it has also three observations such
as the original training data set but
not all of these observations are
different okay the observation with age
23 comes up
twice and the observation with age
70 is missing again the observation with
age 48 is there once and we do this
several times let's say m times and in
other bootstrap samples other
observations may be apparent
more than on such as the 70 H equal 70
observations here in the last bootstrap
sample and others may not show up at all
in these in this bootstrap
sample what we do then is we take these
new data sets and for each data set we
learn a tree separately and
independently of the other trees so this
means we get a lot of trees well that
that's why we call it forest in the end
so we have a lot of trees and all of
these trees are well learned
independently from each other so when we
have a new observation coming in for
prediction of course we have to decide
well what do we do with it so we pass it
through all the trees and then in the
end we need some aggregation rule uh
which tells us um how we um average the
predictions of the different trees and
that in the and is the entire random
forest
model random forests can be used for
classification and regression because
then as space loaders we just use a
classification or regression
trees and as already said at prediction
time nothing really fancy happens
because we have just learned random for
a new supervis machine learning model so
this picture here is the same as usually
always just in the middle we have a
random forest model instead of a tree
learner or instead of a logistic
regression or instead of whatever else
okay so the fancy part is in the
training part in the prediction it just
looks and feels like any other machine
super bied machine learning
model okay I already said if we have
several trees then each tree may give us
a different prediction and now the task
is to aggregate the predictions of the
different tree learners
so let's start here on the left hand
side where we treat a classification
task which means the target variable is
a categorical variable and the in this
case level of happiness again and we
have one observation which we try to
predict so we feed this prediction
through all the trees we feed this
observation through all the trees so we
have five trees in the example and each
tree gives one
classification okay the first and the
fifth say it's pretty happy and the
other three say it's not too happy so
what we can do is taking a majority vote
of these so we have three trees voting
for not too happy we have two trees
voting for pretty happy and we have no
tree predicting the third
category so with taking the majority
WOTE the final random Forest prediction
is not too
happy then on the right hand side we
have a regression task so this means the
target variable is a numerical
variable and again we feed all the uh
features through all the
trees we get five predictions each tree
has a unique or has a has its own
prediction and we can do is for example
just take the average so just the
arithmetic mean of the predictions of
the several trees and then we end up
with one kind of forest prediction that
example it's
4842 okay whatever just some number but
it's the empirical the arithmetic mean
of those five individual tree
predictions one note on the performance
of random forests so well what's not on
the slide but what's also very important
is that random forests usually uh tend
to perform really really well on tabular
data sets it's hard to be random
Forest um very much later you will
perhaps see some uh boosted trees these
perform very well as well but renom
forests are quite well performing models
so that's perhaps the most important
part
here in there's one rule increasing the
assemble size stabilizes the predictions
which you perhaps can see somewhere here
so on the left hand side it's just one
tree on the right hand side we have
50,000 trees which is too much usually
but this somehow this stabilizes the the
prediction but still sometimes for
regression task the stabilization is
often not sufficient sufficient which
means that we need some more tricks
which will learn about of
course but for classification tasks this
works quite nicely so if we first just
have a look at the second row
here we have binary Target variable zero
and one circles and triangles and you
see the decision regions of two random
forests these are a little bit different
you can barely see it because they are
so similar which is good so they are
different because well the reinforce has
two random components that's the
bootstrapping and one thing which I tell
you about on the next slide but still in
the end they are pretty pretty similar
okay which is a which is good and what
in the first row here
is the visualization of two different
classification
trees and what is that they are quite
different okay if you look at this area
here we have a totally different
prediction and this can happen super
super fast if just one observation
changes the entire tree structure can
change so they are very
instable and random forests remedies
this problem of tree
Learners okay now the second trick I
told you about on the slide before so
what we try to do is we try to
decorrelate the trees so we have
different trees now so different Wes
let's say and each of these trees makes
mistakes of course but we want those
trees to make different mistakes because
if each tree makes a different mistake
we can get rid of this problem by
averaging out over the predictions of
all the trees but if all the trees make
the same mistake then averaging doesn't
help at all okay so we avoid this Decor
we avoid correlation by two things it's
the bootstrap sampling so drawing with
replacement from the training data and
by randomizing splits okay what's
randomizing
splits you see here a note of a tree so
here is the
parent data feed here in and we have
some child notes and what happens here
is that in this note or let's start here
we have six features available in the
data set marital status health age sex
and degree and when and searching for
the best split in this Noe we do not
search over all possible features but
first we randomly draw some of those
features so how many features we draw is
the hyperparameter let's say we draw
three features here so we have an random
selection of the features and we just
search for the best splits inside these
three
features and we do this for every note
in every every tree so we take a new
sample every in every note in every tree
which also decorrelates the
trees last but not least there is a nice
thing called feature importance so the
question we try to answer with feature
importance is okay well which feature is
most important for the prediction for
the model of course so as you perhaps
know from statistics with I don't know
some P values or want know how how
important is the
feature and feature importance are the
thing to go with random forest and they
are very there are several options to do
feature or to compute feature
importances out of random forests
one example is here that's the feature
importance based on Improvement in the
splitting criteria there are other and
you will get to know those but that's
just the first glimpse of feature
importances here so how does this work
we have still different trees so each
row here is one tree we have in total M
different trees and now in each tree if
we want to know the feature importance
of the feature
Health we look in each
tree for all the noes where we used
Health as splitting
feature Okay this may be zero one or
several but it can be so yeah can be
several Fe several notes where we used
Health as splitting
feature and then we compute how much
this single
split
improved
some quality measure which you will know
about later but so the question is how
much did this split and just only this
very split in this very not
improve some quality measure then we add
up all those improvements for the tree
then we have the improvement from One
Tree and we do this for all the trees
sum those up and then we have a final
feature importance which tells us in
this case how important the feature
health is for the model predictions